<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mac | Simple Problems]]></title>
  <link href="http://navyapothineni.github.io/blog/categories/mac/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://navyapothineni.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-05T15:06:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://navyapothineni.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Navya Pothineni]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Rogue Daemon]]></title>
    <link href="http://navyapothineni.github.io/blog/2017/04/19/a-rogue-daemon/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-19T17:35:25-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://navyapothineni.github.io/blog/2017/04/19/a-rogue-daemon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I work on a MacBook Pro and in the past few days, I have setup some local servers on my machine, installed a couple of new IDEs, and updated several tools- which seemed to cause noticeable strain. It complained about running out of HDD space and I tried to clear up some unused files and moved some more to an external drive. After persistent performance issues (browser crashes and constant complaints about memory), I looked at the Activity Monitor.</p>

<p>A process named <code>java</code> kept showing up every minute or so with a different PID. Hogging a mind blowing 80-130%CPU, 1-5GB RAM and 20% energy.</p>

<p>To debug this, I booted up my machine in <code>Safe Mode</code> (Hold down the shift key during boot up). Check if the issues persist, if they don&rsquo;t you can be sure that a third party application that isn&rsquo;t essential to the kernel is causing the trouble. Safemode lets you eliminate start up items, any issues pertaining to incompatibility in login applications. It also disables certain extras like user installed fonts, deletes kernel/font/system caches, checks for startup disk issues, etc. If the issue persists however, go back to the Activity Monitor.</p>

<p>Activity Monitor allows you to see the parent PID and name of the parent process by clicking on info. The parent process for me was <code>launchd</code>. It is the program that launches the applications on your Mac. A few searches on the internet led me to do the following. Kill programs that caused automatic updates, like PDF readers, text editors, etc. Also turn off java automatic updates on the Java Control Panel from System Settings. You can look for the parent process that is using java along with the arguments passed using <code>ps</code>.</p>

<pre><code>$ ps axv | grep java
</code></pre>

<p>You should see an output that looks like this.</p>

<pre><code>
2819 ??         0:17.00 /usr/bin/java -Xloggc:/usr/local/Cellar/cassandra/3.7/libexec/logs/gc.log -ea -XX:+UseThreadPriorities -XX:ThreadPriorityPolicy=42 -XX:+HeapDumpOnOutOfMemoryError -Xss256k -XX:StringTableSize=1000003 -XX:+AlwaysPreTouch -XX:-UseBiasedLocking -XX:+UseTLAB -XX:+ResizeTLAB -XX:+PerfDisableSharedMem -Djava.net.preferIPv4Stack=true -XX:+UseParNewGC -XX:+UseConcMarkSweepGC -XX:+CMSParallelRemarkEnabled -XX:SurvivorRatio=8 -XX:MaxTenuringThreshold=1 -XX:CMSInitiatingOccupancyFraction=75 -XX:+UseCMSInitiatingOccupancyOnly -XX:CMSWaitDuration=10000
</code></pre>

<p>In my case, it was a daemon process that was starting Cassandra and creating tables similar to a stress daemon process. I uninstalled Cassandra and deleted data, properties and log dirs soon after. <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/10877072/stop-cassandra-server-on-mac-os-x">This</a> is a helpful discussion on how to spot problems like this one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
